Support Admin Watch on
kissasia.cam or kisskh.org
Whoa!
Try to dodge this.
Stay back.
You're all useless.
Can't even teach one laborer a lesson.
Brother, are you all right?
- You're gonna regret that.
- You're making a fool of yourself.
Just let it go.
My wage.
Hand it over.
They didn't pay us either.
Strike the petition drum if you want.
You want to die over one doe of rice?
Do it.
Do it!
If I find out this is all a lie,
you're as good as dead.
The Murky Stream
TWO. THE WIND THAT STIRS IN MAPO
- What now, brother?
- What?
Huh? What about the boat charge
- and labor charge we pocketed?
- Will you shut it?
They'll catch us.
And we'll be in big trouble.
- Don't you think so?
- I said shut it.
A little risk isn't worth the reward? Huh?
Let's go!
You're going?
All of them got injured, though.
It's hardship, so what?
We're bandits. We turn our backs.
I gotta piss.
Be careful as you carry that.
How dare you?
Where do you think you are?
Stop!
What do you want?
I'm here to collect my wages from you.
What are you saying?
No one received their wages
after the lady here went boating.
We merchants pay right away.
We don't make deals on credit.
But even so, no one was given payment.
One side says that they gave it.
The other side says
they never received it.
So, tell me, to whom do I enquire
to receive my wage?
I see you haven't had enough.
We said that we paid you all.
The Mapo bandits are likely at fault.
Talk to that lot.
Someone ordered our work.
Yet no one claims responsibility
for our payment.
"It's not me. Go ask them."
"And it wasn't us either.
Go ask again."
We work ourselves to death
for just one doe of rice.
How long will you have us
dancing around in circles?
I've heard enough out of you, young man.
We are not the ones who pocketed it.
How dare you cause a scene?
Chief Kang!
- What do you think you're doing?
- Are you all right?
You didn't say a word to those bandits.
But women are easier
to pick on, aren't they?
Here... Exchange this,
and you'll get one mal of rice at least.
I don't need your charity.
This is my wage.
Can't you be courteous?
Are you truly asking
for trouble right now?
Take it with you and leave.
How can you treat us this way?
It's like we're animals.
Do you think you can just use your money
to bribe us and order us around?
Well, that isn't usually
how I treat people,
but you seem to deserve it.
You've proven you'd punch anyone
for a little money.
Try starving for three days...
for a single doe of rice.
You'd be willing to untie
your pretty sash.
Really?
Then I dare you...
untie it.
What's wrong?
You're reckless, but not brave enough?
Halt.
Don't be so impolite to the lady.
Perhaps it's time
somebody taught you a lesson?
It isn't worth starting a fight.
That's enough. Follow me.
This is my share.
I'll give the rest to the other laborers.
- What's taking so long?
- He's coming.
What did she say?
So... so what did you find out?
Huh? Tell us.
- Say something.
- This is our wage from the guild.
Hey, hey.
I got it. I got it.
- Are you all right?
- Are you positive you paid the wages?
Of course.
Someone must have taken it.
Damn you.
Give it to me.
That's Mapo for you.
Some drifter did this to you?
And I'm ashamed of it.
That why you didn't tell me?
If we're crushed,
isn't it our law to never admit to it?
Hey,
if you were going to fight alone,
what was the point of joining the clan?
Huh?
No matter how strong a Tiger is,
it cannot fight
a pack of wolves on its own.
I'll keep that in mind, brother.
Huh.
Interesting.
You want to work out of Joseon?
I heard, you know, martial arts
and were a general of a Jurchen Tribe.
But with five men alone,
you can't take the Gyeonggang River.
You would be dealing with violent thugs.
Do you not think this is foolish?
That's why I'm here asking you to help me.
You must help me, too, then.
It's only fair.
Of course I will.
Otherwise you wouldn't agree.
Look at this.
It's a map of the Hanyang area.
The Gyeonggang River
is surrounded by the sea.
It's convenient
for reaching other regions.
If you're willing to look outward,
then your profits could be
greater than you ever imagined.
So smuggling is your idea.
If I take over the Gyeonggang River,
half of the profit
will be returned to you.
Listen well.
Hmm.
Your strength doesn't matter here.
If you disobey the law, it's over.
This country belongs to His Majesty.
And don't forget,
His Majesty is always watching.
Choi Jeongyeop.
He is not suitable.
What are you going to do now?
I need to find someone greedier
and more powerful.
Do you truly mean to build
a new foundation on this land?
Now is the time.
I cannot let my brothers and my children
live as subjects of Mongol.
I would rather die than see that happen.
Will I be able to live
with my child and my wife?
Of course.
For their sake,
we must take over the Gyeonggang River.
Brother.
Oh, shit.
This is not good.
What?
Yoon said he wants to have
a chat with you right now.
- What for?
- Ah, it's the money we pocketed
from the boat and all the labor.
- Yeah?
- Ahh! Malbok was talking about it
while taking a piss
and he got caught.
What a damn idiot.
- That damn babbler!
- We're in trouble.
Everybody knows
that Yoon's temper is really bad.
What do we do now?
Why are you asking me?
I think we're both going
to end up dead today.
Line up in order of seniority,
and start from there.
Right there, yes. Yes.
That's right.
There are some things
you can and cannot pocket,
and yet you pocketed the laborer's wages.
I apologize.
Excuse me.
I think this is
all a misunderstanding.
Please, keep on talking.
Hey, you're up first.
Yes, sir.
It'll go up by seniority.
- I swear I'll be better.
- All right. Next. Come on.
Oh, no. Oh, no.
What? You feeling sick?
Get down.
The hell is wrong with you?
You're up next.
Now, come on.
- Uh, boss, about my backdoor.
- What's wrong?
- It gets kind of sensitive there.
- I'll just poke it.
- No. Oh, no.
- Or I can beat it. You choose.
- Go! Stand there.
- No, no. Don't.
- Yeah, that's good.
- Wait.
Forgive me.
Back in line. Next.
Want me to hit your arm instead, huh?
Stop, please.
Why, why, why?
Come on.
Brother, your turn.
What are you waiting for?
Hurry and get over here.
- Come here now.
- Yoon.
Yes, boss?
That'll do for now.
What the hell are you smiling at?
I'm sorry. I was in such a rush.
I meant to let you know much sooner.
Is that so?
My actions were very wrong.
I'll reflect on myself.
Stand straighter. Chest out.
Uh, brother, wait.
Do you have to do this
with the young ones watching?
Yeah, they should see this.
I helped you when you begged
on the streets.
You remember that.
- I appreciate it.
- Yeah.
Stand up straight.
Shoulders up now, like a man.
Huh?
Square your shoulders. Like that, good.
Why did you do that
when you knew better?
Why disappoint me?
From now on,
I... I won't disappoint you again.
That will do.
Open up your shoulders again.
Stand up straight.
Yoon.
I said that'll do.
Fucking bastard!
How can I respect you
when you don't act your age, huh?
You're not worth the time and energy,
but you never shut up.
If you try something like this again,
- Okay.
- I don't care how old you are,
- I'm gonna lose it.
- Understood.
If it hadn't been
for Brother Deokgae interrupting us,
you'd be in a coffin.
Now, fuck off.
First one back is spared!
- Yes, sir!
Brother!
Out of my way!
Mudeok.
Yes?
Come here. Have a drink.
No, thank you. I'm all right.
Take it.
Huh?
You don't have to kneel.
Oh, I'm comfortable. Thank you.
Are you all right?
- Oh, yes.
- Then drink.
A... All right.
Would you allow me
to pour you a drink?
Don't call me boss here.
We're friends.
Just Deokgae is fine.
Oh, no, boss.
Relax. It's just us.
You fool.
Boss.
I really do think
this was all a misunderstanding.
Mudeok, look.
Yes?
It's all right.
I understand.
We started this life together.
I rose to a thumb,
but you're still struggling
out in the streets.
Plus you're constantly beaten
and challenged by the younger men.
It must be hard.
I keep thinking about that.
And Mudeok...
This life just isn't right for you.
Oh, wait. Wait, but I...
I'm not done yet.
I see.
Why don't you return to your hometown?
You owe, what?
Two cows worth for gambling.
Is that about eighty nyang?
How's this? I'll settle it for you.
Think about it.
You've got no fists and no guts.
Your liver is about
the size of a walnut.
You know, you're soft-hearted.
Go fishing.
Catch anchovies.
Doesn't that sound nice?
D... Deokgae.
You mean...
You... you mean to say I should quit?
Deokgae. Deokgae, I won't do it again.
I'm not going back to my hometown.
I'm not even sure whether or not
my parents are still alive.
How can I go back there? Hmm?
I swear I could do a lot better.
Hmm?
Deokgae, let me
let me pour you one glass.
Let's head back, Brother!
Brother!
Let's go!
Leave me alone!
Bastards!
Walwal.
Yes, brother.
That kid.
The one who beat
Bang to the ground.
Where is he?
He must have left.
And if he's caught,
they'll beat him to death.
He won't return.
Set it aside.
I'm sick of that book.
Why do you take the state exams
again and again?
We have the trade.
- You should learn it.
- Father.
What's the point of having so much money
when I'd just be a merchant.
So the trade's not good enough?
Confucius said,
"There are four social classes,"
of those classes,
the last one listed is the merchant.
Your legacy is here.
I've poured all my blood and sweat
- into protecting this guild.
- Be that as it may.
You already know
this work doesn't suit me.
You're a fool.
If not you, then who?
Eun is right there, father.
- But she's a girl.
- She's more capable than most men are.
Yet you refuse
to acknowledge this.
Father.
I'll learn how to be a merchant.
Hey, hey.
I'm good with arithmetic, you said so.
I promise if Daeil ever wants anything,
I'll give him salt, wood,
or anything at all.
All right?
I can do this.
We should eat.
The ledger.
I think I might give it to Eun.
So... teaching her is your plan?
What can I do?
The only son I have shunts his legacy.
She may be a lady, but she's clever.
Quite strong-willed too.
She isn't afraid to speak her mind.
You two are similar.
You can stop now.
She has all the qualities you want.
She could take over the guild.
It's temporary.
Daeil will make a decision.
- Only until then.
- Sure.
A new face, huh?
He's right over there.
Move. Move it.
Hey, brother.
You busy?
Why aren't you answering?
Huh?
- Did you come here to collect my taxes?
- Look at you.
Aren't you a smart one.
He must be a noble.
Do you want a lesson?
First off, the permission fee
is two mal of rice.
The street fee is half a doe.
If the Police Bureau comes
for an inspection,
it's two hops of rice.
Understood?
Since I have nothing now
could I pay you once I sell my wood?
That's a no.
You can trust me.
All right.
Let's go.
I swear, I'll pay you.
I'm a man of my word.
I told you to go.
You're something else.
Hey. What's with this glare then?
Huh? Guess you don't wanna
keep your head.
Oh, don't be like that.
- You don't have to act so serious.
- Look at him glaring!
Don't be so mean right from the start.
Look here, pretty boy.
I'll only say this once,
because you're good-looking.
See? That way.
All the way over there
is the West Gate.
No one's there.
There'll be no taxes.
Thank you for that.
Hey, wait.
Leave that here.
I bought this carrier
with everything I had.
I see no reason to give it to you.
What passes through this alley
belongs to us.
That's just Seosomun's law. So leave it.
You don't wanna do this.
Just let me leave.
You're pressing your luck here.
Hey.
Why don't I show you
who's boss, huh?
Ow! Oh, my arm, my arm.
My arm, my arm, my arm.
Oh, please, please.
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
It hurts. It hurts.
Let's stop here.
I have no reason to fight anyone else.
Tha... That's him.
He's the one who beat up Bang.
- What? Really?
- Yes.
I hear he grabbed him and knocked him out.
Apparently, he hasn't woken up yet.
That must be him, then.
The Mokpo swordsman.
- The swordsman?
- Uh-huh.
He beat a dozen men all by himself.
To make sure they were dead,
he skinned and filleted
their chests like fish.
I heard he munched the innards.
What the hell?
That man's not a human. He's a monster.
There will be
a bloodbath in Mapo soon.
Mark my words.
What if he becomes
the next thumb?
Now that's a fire I want to see.
- Gaedal.
- Who's there?
It's me.
Mudeok. What brings you here?
Okay. All right.
Keep a lookout for me.
Yeah, go ahead.
Here, this bundle, it's all he left.
- You better go.
- Okay.
Ah, shit.
Something's around here.
Oh! You're back.
Why are you back early today?
Oh, I see.
Wait, what is this?
Did you get robbed
by the Seosomun bandits there?
Oh, you poor thing.
Well, are you all right?
I'm fine.
I'm just glad you're safe.
Any wounds? Are you hurt?
No?
Ah. All right.
Well, you must be tired.
Get some rest inside.
Get your ass in there.
What the hell does it say? Hmm.
He passed
the last military state exam
with the highest record.
He is Jung Chun.
He's from Gyeongwonji, Hamgyeong-do.
Straight to the mark!
Officer Jung Chun reporting.
I was selected
for the Police Bureau, General.
Assistant Officer. Newly appointed.
I hear you were the finest
among those who passed the exam.
It's an honor, sir.
Any family history?
- Has anyone served in office?
- None, sir.
I will be the first one.
What a humble family you have.
This is his first post.
So I ask that you offer him guidance.
First things first, a celebration.
Going forward your top priority
is guarding His Majesty.
By doing so he can continue
to look after the people.
Do you understand?
I will keep that in mind.
You are dismissed.
Thank you.
I'll go back to my duty, sir.
All right.
I'm Captain Park.
I oversee the central territories.
And I'm Captain Oh,
in charge of the east.
You can call me Captain Ji,
I oversee the south.
Since this is my first day,
I'll require a lot of help from you.
I look forward to working together.
Yes, of course.
We are all here to help you.
Well, then, could I see
your inspection log?
Huh?
Well, you see, normally that isn't a task
you'd do on your first day.
Every single day,
the three of us run inspections,
so there's no need to worry.
Why aren't you moving? Go get it.
- Oh, yes, sir.
- Yes, sir.
Wow. How nice.
It's beautiful.
Please accept this gift.
Congratulations on your appointment.
What's the meaning of this?
Um, it's actually customary.
Yes, and you're expected to receive it.
You should follow the rules.
Well, we'll get going now.
Lots to prepare for your procession.
Is that really necessary?
Uh, I think that people
want to see you out there.
You should show them your authority.
It's a chance to meet them face-to-face
and, well, listen to their grievances.
Sir, why don't we start
with the village outskirts?
Ah, good idea. You'd enjoy it.
The outskirts are filled
with wickedness.
Now, sir...
Come with us.
The bureau, you see,
has customs you'll need to get used to.
We're getting ready
for a procession on your behalf.
Let's go.
- Captain!
- An Assistant Officer...
receiving a nice bribe from the captains
as soon as he arrives.
It's okay. That's how you get
started around here.
Please understand.
It's the custom
to share what you receive.
Keep this in mind.
The left side of the police bureau
is under your watch.
I take the right side.
If you mess with my side
without permission,
then you'll be sorry.
What do you think, brother?
He seems pretty uptight.
He learned the world from books.
So what would he know?
He'll get used to it.
Get ready for his party.
Our guild uses the bridge in Sampo.
Deokgae's the one
in charge of collecting taxes.
Taxes?
So the country's taxes
are collected by the bandits?
No, not quite.
These are different charges.
There's an additional charge
when loading and unloading goods.
A rush charge for if the order changes,
a torch charge for night work,
bridge charges for repairs.
But that's unjust.
They're taking advantage of us.
We pay the bandits money
to get them to do our bidding.
If you don't feel like going,
you don't have to.
But if it's worth the money,
a merchant would do anything at all,
even bow down.
What do you say, my lady?
Then I have no choice.
There's no turning back.
Let's go.
Shut up, shut up.
Oh, brother.
I have someone to introduce.
The young leader of our guild.
She'll be in charge of salt and silk,
so treat her with respect.
Just call me Yoon.
Do you want to have a drink with us?
Lady, that look is kinda scary.
It's only her first time here.
She's truly a brave and generous person.
- Oh!
- Well, here.
This is from her.
Go and buy yourselves a drink.
Wow. I'd offer a bow,
but my knee's aren't doing so good.
Young lady, thanks it means a lot.
Is your boss here with you?
We'd like to talk.
Could you let him know
He's over at the tavern.
You know what?
You should head over and say hi.
Yeah?
My lady...
Let's come back another time.
I'd rather not. Please lead the way.
Wow. Wow.
This bitch.
Chief Kang, what brings you
all the way to the tavern?
Well, it was time for an introduction.
This is our new young leader.
We're here to ask for your cooperation.
Choi's guild had a son,
least what I heard.
Why would his daughter wanna join us
down this rough path?
Is this how you greet
your future business partners?
I know you're treating me like this
because I'm a woman.
How about you consider it
a part of becoming friends.
I'm Mapo's thumb, Deokgae.
Here.
Why don't you have a drink?
That drink is
too strong for a woman.
I'm not sure she'll be okay.
Of course not.
She could never drink
something that strong.
You don't have to drink it.
- Seomsoem here.
- Yes.
Oh, my.
Oh, oh wow!
Oh, she's gulping it down!
She's gulping it down!
- Good job!
- Good job.
I'm dying here.
Drink another.
Well done.
I don't intend to pay unfair taxes.
I highly suggest
you all keep this in mind.
Suit yourself then.
Boats will be unloaded
in the order they are docked,
so there won't be
a need for a rush charge.
The authorities inspect cargo,
so if you charge for inspection,
I shall report it to the police.
What an innocent subject you are.
Do you still think
the authorities are trustworthy?
Looks like Choi's Guild is in good hands.
Whaddya think?
There's a bright future ahead!
Let's cheers to that!
It was so nice to meet you.
Just don't expect
to get much help from me.
However, my bandits are helpful.
A lot more helpful than the authorities.
To becoming rich.
To becoming rich!
That kind of person...
I truly despise.
My lady.
What they said is true.
The bandits... they're much more helpful
than the authorities.
Are you all right?
- I'll carry your veil.
- No, I'm fine.
Why did you drink that strong liquor?
Brother Yoon!
I found him!
The one who had that big fight with Bang.
- Where the hell is he?
- He's over at the West Gate.
I was passing by and I saw him out there
selling wood with my own eyes.
Go get me Bang.
Hold on. Do we need this many?
There's a rumor. That rogue,
he's apparently a swordsman.
Remember you told me
not even a tiger can defeat a wolf pack.
Yeah, I suppose I did.
- Let's go.
- Come on.
Here we go!
Come on, come on.
There he is.
Bang, is that him?
Yeah.
Let's go say hello.
That bastard.
- Brother! Brother! Look, look.
- What?
GYEONGWON
JUNG CHUN
Come on. Hurry, hurry.
Make way!
Here comes the newly appointed
assistant officer!
Out of the way!
Make way.
Hold a moment.
Siyul.
You rascal.
I see you're not dead.
JUNG CHUN